<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "../Coding_Standards.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<chapter id="chap-Coding_Standards-PHP">
  <title>PHP</title>

  <para>This chapter is about ...</para>

  <section>
    <title>Language Constructs</title>

    <section>
      <title>PHP Code Tags</title>

      <para>Always use the full &lt;?php ?&gt; to delimit PHP code, not the &lt;? ?&gt; shorthand. This is the most portable way
      to include PHP code on differing operating systems and setups.</para>

      <para>For files that contain only PHP code, the closing tag (?&gt;) should not be included. It is not required by PHP.
      Leaving this out prevents trailing white space from being accidentally injected into the output that can introduce errors in
      the Joomla session (see the PHP manual on <ulink url="http://php.net/basic-syntax.instruction-separation">Instruction separation</ulink>.</para>

      <para>Files should always end with a blank new line.</para>

      <para>TODO Example</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Including Code</title>

      <para>Anywhere you are unconditionally including a file, use require_once. Anywhere you are conditionally including a file
      (for example, factory methods), use include_once. Either of these will ensure that files are included only once. They share
      the same file list, so you don't need to worry about mixing them. A file included with require_once will not be included
      again by include_once.</para>

      <note>
        <para>include_once and require_once are PHP language statements, not functions. The correct formatting is:</para>

        <para><code>require_once JPATH_COMPONENT.’/helpers/helper.php’;</code></para>
      </note>

      <para>You should not enclose the filename in parentheses.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>E_STRICT Compatible PHP Code</title>

      <para>As of Joomla version 1.6 and for all versions of the Joomla Platform, adhering to object oriented programming practice
      as supported by PHP 5.2 is required. Joomla is committed to progressively making the source code E_STRICT.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Global Variables</title>

    <para>TODO Usage should be kept to a minimum. Use OOP and factory patterns instead.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Control Structures</title>

    <para>For all control structures there is a space between the keyword and an opening parenthesis, then no space either after
    the opening parenthesis or before the closing bracket. This is done to distinguish control keywords from function names. All
    control structures must contain their logic within braces.</para>

    <para>For all all control structures, such as if, else, do, for, foreach, try, catch, switch and while, both the keyword
    starts a newline and the opening and closing braces are each put on a new line.</para>

    <section>
      <title>An if-else Example</title>

      <programlisting>if ($test)
{
	echo 'True';
}
// Comments can go here.
// Note that "elseif" as one word is used.
elseif ($test === false)
{
	echo 'Really false';
}
else
{
	echo 'A white lie';
}</programlisting>

      <para>If a control structure goes over multiple lines, all lines must be indented with one tab and the closing brace must go
      on the same line as the last parameter.</para>

      <example>
        <title>Multi line if statement</title>

        <para><programlisting>if ($test1
    &amp;&amp; $test2)
{
    echo 'True';
}</programlisting></para>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>A do-while Example</title>

      <programlisting>do
{
    $i++;
}
while ($i &lt; 10);</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>A for Example</title>

      <programlisting>for ($i = 0; $i &lt; $n; $i++)
{
    echo 'Increment = '.$i;
}</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>A foreach Example</title>

      <programlisting>foreach ($rows as $index =&gt; $row)
{
    echo 'Index = '.$id.', Value = '.$row;
}</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>A while Example</title>

      <programlisting>while (!$done)
{
    $done = true;
}</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>A switch example</title>

      <para>When using a switch statement, the case keywords are indented. The break statement starts on a newline assuming the
      indent of the code within the case.</para>

      <programlisting>switch ($value)
{
    case 'a':
        echo 'A';
        break;

    default:
        echo 'I give up';
        break;
}</programlisting>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>References</title>

      <para>When using references, there should be a space before the reference operator and no space between it and the function
      or variable name.</para>

      <para>For example:</para>

      <programlisting>&lt;?php
$ref1 = &amp;$this-&gt;sql;</programlisting>

      <note>
        <para>In PHP 5, reference operators are not required for objects. All objects are handled by reference.</para>
      </note>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Arrays</title>

      <para>Assignments (the =&gt; operator) in arrays may be aligned with tabs. When splitting array definitions onto several
      lines, the last value may also have a trailing comma. This is valid PHP syntax and helps to keep code diffs minimal.</para>

      <para>For example:</para>

      <programlisting>$options = array(
    'foo'  =&gt; 'foo',
    'spam' =&gt; 'spam',
);</programlisting>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Code Commenting</title>

    <para>Inline comments to explain code follow the convention for C (/* … */) and C++ single line (// ...) comments. C-style
    blocks are generally restricted to documentation headers for files, classes and functions. The C++ style is generally used for
    making code notes. Code notes are strongly encouraged to help other people, including your future-self, follow the purpose of
    the code. Always provide notes where the code is performing particularly complex operations.</para>

    <para>Perl/shell style comments (#) are not permitted in PHP files but are permitted in INI language files.</para>

    <para>Blocks of code may, of course, be commented out for debugging purposes using any appropriate format, but should be
    removed before submitting patches for contribution back to the core code.</para>

    <para>For example, do not include feature submissions like:</para>

    <programlisting>&lt;?php
// Must fix this code up one day.
//$code = broken($fixme);</programlisting>

    <section>
      <title>Comment Docblocks</title>

      <para>Documentation headers for PHP and Javascript code in files, classes, class properties, methods and functions, called
      the docblocks, follow a convention similar to JavaDoc or phpDOC.</para>

      <para>These "DocBlocks" borrow from the PEAR standard but have some variations specific for Joomla and the Joomla
      Platform.</para>

      <para>Whereas normal code indenting uses real tabs, all whitespace in a Docblock uses real spaces. This provides better
      readability in source code browsers. The minimum whitespace between any text elements, such as tags, variable types,
      variable names and tag descriptions, is two real spaces. Variable types and tag descriptions should be aligned according to
      the longest Docblock tag and type-plus-variable respectively.</para>

      <para>If the @package tag is used, it will be "Joomla.Platform".</para>

      <para>If the @subpackage tag is used, it is the name of the top level folder under the /joomla/ folder. For example:
      Application, Database, Html, and so on.</para>

      <para>Code contributed to the Joomla project that will become the copyright of the project is not allowed to include @author
      tags. You should update the contribution log in CREDITS.php. Joomla's philosophy is that the code is written "all together"
      and there is no notion of any one person "owning" any section of code. The @author tags are permitted in third-party
      libraries that are included in the core libraries.</para>

      <para>Files included from third party sources must leave DocBlocks intact. Layout files use the same DocBlocks as other PHP
      files.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>File DocBlock Headers</title>

      <para>The file header DocBlock consists of the following required and optional elements in the following order:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Short description (optional unless the file contains more than two classes or functions), followed by a blank
          line).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Long description (optional, followed by a blank line).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>@category (optional and rarely used)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>@package (generally optional but required when files contain only procedural code)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>@subpackage (optional)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>@author (optional but only permitted in non-Joomla source files, for example, included third-party libraries like
          Geshi)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>@copyright (required)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>@license (required and must be compatible with the Joomla license)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>@deprecated (optional)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>@link (optional)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>@see (optional)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>@since (generally optional but required when files contain only procedural code)</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <example>
        <title>Example Joomla Platform file header</title>

        <programlisting>&lt;?php
/**
 * @package     Joomla.Platform
 * @subpackage  Database
 * @copyright   Copyright 2005 - 2010 Open Source Matters. All rights re-served.
 * @license     GNU General Public License version 2 or later; see LICENSE.txt
 */</programlisting>
      </example>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Function Calls</title>

    <para>Functions should be called with no spaces between the function name and the opening parenthesis, and no space between
    this and the first parameter; a space after the comma between each parameter (if they are present), and no space between the
    last parameter and the closing parenthesis. There should be space before and exactly one space after the equals sign. Tab
    alignment over multiple lines is permitted.</para>

    <example>
      <title>Example function call</title>

      <programlisting>&lt;?php
// An isolated function call.
$foo = bar($var1, $var2);

// Multiple aligned function calls.
$short   = bar('short');
$medium  = bar('medium');
$long    = bar('long');</programlisting>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Function Definitions</title>

    <para>Function definitions start on a new line and the opening and closing braces are also placed on new lines. An empty line
    should precede lines specifying the return value.</para>

    <para>Function definitions must include a documentation comment in accordance with the Commenting section of this
    document.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Short description (required, followed by a blank line)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Long description (optional, followed by a blank line)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>@param (required if there are method or function arguments, the last @param tag is followed by a blank line)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>@return (required, followed by a blank line)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>All other tags in alphabetical order, however @since is always required.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <example>
      <title>Example function definition with docblock</title>

      <para><programlisting>&lt;?php
/**
 * A utility class.
 *
 * @package     Joomla.Platform
 * @subpackage  XBase
 *
 * @param       string  $path  The library path in dot notation.
 *
 * @return      void
 *
 * @since       1.6
 */
function jimport($path)
{
    // Body of method.
}</programlisting></para>
    </example>

    <para>If a function definition goes over multiple lines, all lines must be indented with one tab and the closing brace must go
    on the same line as the last parameter.</para>

    <example>
      <title>Multi line function definition</title>

      <programlisting>function fooBar($param1, $param2,
   $param3, $param4)
{
   // Body of method.
}</programlisting>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Class Definitions</title>

    <para>Class definitions start on a new line and the opening and closing braces are also placed on new lines. Class methods
    must follow the guidelines for Function Definitions. Properties and methods must follow OOP standards and be declared
    appropriately (using public, protected, private and static as applicable).</para>

    <para>Class definitions, properties and methods must each be provided with a DocBlock in accordance with the following
    sections.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Class DocBlock Headers</title>

      <para>The class Docblock consists of the following required and optional elements in the fol-lowing order.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Short description (required, unless the file contains more than two classes or functions), followed by a blank
          line).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Long description (optional, followed by a blank line).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>@category (optional and rarely used)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>@package (required)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>@subpackage (optional)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>@author (optional but only permitted in non-Joomla source files, for example, included third-party libraries like
          Geshi)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>@copyright (optional unless different from the file Docblock)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>@license (optional unless different from the file Docblock)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>@deprecated (optional)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>@link (optional)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>@see (optional)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>@since (required, being the version of the software the class was introduced)</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Class Property DocBlocks</title>

      <para>The class property Docblock consists of the following required and optional elements in the following order.</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Short description (required, followed by a blank line)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>@var (required, followed by the property type)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>@deprecated (optional)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>@since (required)</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Class Method DocBlocks</title>

      <para>The DocBlock for class methods follows the same convention as for PHP functions (see above).</para>

      <example>
        <title>Example class definition</title>

        <programlisting>&lt;?php
/**
 * A utility class.
 *
 * @package     Joomla.Platform
 * @subpackage  XBase
 * @since       1.6
 */
class JClass extends JObject
{
    /**
     * Human readable name
     *
     * @var    string
     * @since  1.6
     */
    public $name;

    /**
     * Method to get the name of the class.
     *
     * @param   string  $case  Optionally return in upper/lower case.
     *
     * @return  boolean  True if successfully loaded, false otherwise.
     *
     * @since   1.6
     */
    public function getName($case = null)
    {
        // Body of method.

        return $this-&gt;name;
    }
}</programlisting>
      </example>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Naming Conventions</title>

    <section>
      <title>Classes</title>

      <para>Classes should be given descriptive names. Avoid using abbreviations where possible. Class names should always begin
      with an uppercase letter and be written in CamelCase even if using traditionally uppercase acronyms (such as XML, HTML). One
      exception is for Joomla framework classes which must begin with an uppercase 'J' with the next letter also being
      uppercase.</para>

      <para>For example:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>JHtmlHelper</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>JXmlParser</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>JModel</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Functions and Methods</title>

      <para>Functions and methods should be named using the "studly caps" style (also referred to as "bumpy case" or "camel
      caps"). The initial letter of the name is lowercase, and each letter that starts a new "word" is capitalized. Function in
      the Joomla framework must begin with a lowercase 'j'.</para>

      <para>For example:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>connect();</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>getData();</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>buildSomeWidget();</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>jImport();</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>jDoSomething();</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>Private class members (meaning class members that are intended to be used only from within the same class in which
      they are declared) are preceded by a single underscore. Properties are to be written in underscore format (that is, logical
      words separated by underscores) and should be all lowercase.</para>

      <para>For example:</para>

      <example>
        <title>Example class with private properties (DocBlocks excluded for clarity)</title>

        <programlisting>class JFooHelper
{
    private $_status = null;

    protected $field_name = null;

    protected function sort()
    {
    }
}</programlisting>
      </example>

      <note>
        <para>Private class methods, and properties, should be avoided unless absolutely necessary as they present difficulties
        when writing unit tests.</para>
      </note>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Constants</title>

      <para>Constants should always be all-uppercase, with underscores to separate words. Prefix constant names with the uppercase
      name of the class/package they are used in. For example, the constants used by the JError class all begin with
      "JERROR_".</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Global Variables</title>

      <para>Do not use global variables. Use static class properties or constants instead of globals.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Regular Variables and Class Properties</title>

      <para>Regular variables, follow the same conventions as function.</para>

      <para>Class variables should be set to null or some other appropriate default value.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Exception Handling</title>

    <para>Exceptions should be used for error handling.</para>

    <para>The follow sections outline how to semantically use <ulink url="http://php.net/manual/en/spl.exceptions.php">SPL exceptions</ulink>.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Logic Exceptions</title>

      <para>The <exceptionname>LogicException</exceptionname> is used when there is an explicit problem with the way the API is
      being used. For example:</para>

      <simplelist>
        <member>A dependency has failed (you try to operate on an object that has not been loaded yet).</member>
      </simplelist>

      <para>The following child classes can also be used in appropriate situations.</para>

      <section>
        <title>BadFunctionCallException</title>

        <para>This exception can be thrown if a callback refers to an undefined function or if some arguments are missing. For
        example:</para>

        <simplelist>
          <member><methodname>is_callable</methodname>, or similar, fails on a function.</member>
        </simplelist>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>BadMethodCallException</title>

        <para>This exception can be thrown if a callback refers to an undefined method or if some arguments are missing. For
        example:</para>

        <simplelist>
          <member><methodname>is_callable</methodname>, or similar, fails on a class method.</member>
          <member>Arguments passed to a magic call method are missing.</member>
        </simplelist>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>InvalidArgumentException</title>

        <para>This exception can be called if there is invalid input.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>DomainException</title>

        <para>This exception is similar to the <exceptionname>InvalidArgumentException</exceptionname> but can be thrown if a
        value does not adhere to a defined valid data domain. For example:</para>

        <simplelist>
          <member>Trying to load a database driver of type "mongodb" but that driver is not available in the API.</member>
        </simplelist>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>LengthException</title>

        <para>This exception can be thrown is a length check on an argument fails. For example:</para>

        <simplelist>
          <member>A file signature was not a specific number of characters.</member>
        </simplelist>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>OutOfRangeException</title>

        <para>This exception has few practical applications but can be thrown when an illegal index was requested.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Runtime Exceptions</title>

      <para>The <exceptionname>RuntimeException</exceptionname> is thrown when some sort of external entity or environment causes
      a problem that is beyond your control providing the input is valid. This exception is the default case for when the cause of
      an error can't explicitly be determined. For example:</para>

      <simplelist>
        <member>Tried to connect to a database but the database was not available (server down, etc).</member>

        <member>An SQL query failed.</member>
      </simplelist>

      <section>
        <title>UnexpectedValueException</title>

        <para>This type of exception should be used when an unexpected result is encountered. For example:</para>

        <simplelist>
          <member>A function call returned a string when a boolean was expected.</member>
        </simplelist>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>OutOfBoundsException</title>

        <para>This exception has few practical applications but may be thrown if a value is not a valid key.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>OverflowException</title>

        <para>This exception has few practical applications but may be thrown when you add an element into a full
        container.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>RangeException</title>

        <para>This exception has few practical applications but may be thrown to indicate range errors during program execution.
        Normally this means there was an arithmetic error other than under/overflow. This is the runtime version of
        DomainException.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>UnderflowException</title>

        <para>This exception has few practical applications but may thrown when you try to remove an element of an empty
        container.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Documenting exceptions</title>

      <para>Each function or method must annotate the type of exception that it throws using an @throws tag and any downstream
      exceptions types that are thrown. Each type of exception need only be annotated once. No description is necessary.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>SQL Queries</title>

    <para>SQL keywords are to be written in uppercase, while all other identifiers (which the ex-ception of quoted text obviously)
    is to be in lowercase.</para>

    <para>All table names should use the #__ prefix rather than jos_ to access Joomla contents and allow for the user defined
    database prefix to be applied. Queries should also use the JDatabaseQuery API.</para>

    <example>
      <title>Example query</title>

      <programlisting>// Get the database connector.
$db = JFactory::getDBO();

// Get the query from the database connector.
$query = $db-&gt;getQuery(true);

// Build the query programatically (using chaining if desired).
$query-&gt;select('u.*')
    // Use the qn alias for the quoteName method to quote table names.
    -&gt;from($db-&gt;qn('#__users').' AS u'));

// Tell the database connector what query to run.
$db-&gt;setQuery($query);

// Invoke the query or data retrieval helper.
$users = $db-&gt;loadObjectList();</programlisting>
    </example>
  </section>
</chapter>
