<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE preface PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "Joomla_Platform_Manual.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<appendix id="appe-Joomla_Platform_Manual-Analysis">
  <title>Configuring Code Analysis Tools</title>

  <section>
    <title>Running Unit Tests</title>

    <para>Before code gets pulled into the master repository, the unit testing suite is run to ensure that the change candidates
    to not leave trunk in an unstable state (i.e. all tests should pass at all times). In order to make the process of getting
    your code accepted it is helpful to run these tests locally to prevent any unexpected surprises.</para>

    <para>The Joomla Platform unit tests are developed for use with PHPUnit 3.5, which is the latest stable version as of August
    2011. Please see the <ulink url="http://www.phpunit.de/manual/3.5/en/installation.html">PHPUnit Manual</ulink> for information
    on installing PHPUnit on your system.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Configuring Your Environment: The Database</title>

      <para>At this point in time you will get a bunch of failed unit tests if you attempt to execute them without first creating
      a database, populating it, and configuring the unit tests to be able to locate the correct database using the correct
      user.</para>

      <para>To do this, perform the following steps:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Create a database and a database user with full access to the database.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Populate the database by executing the ddl.sql file found in the tests directory.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Copy the config.php-dist file to config.php (in the tests directory) and edit the host, user, password and db
          values as appropriate (this step can be skipped if your database is on localhost, is named joomla_ut, your user is named
          utuser and the password is ut1234.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

	<section>
		<title>Configuring Your Environment: The JHttpTransport Test Stubs</title>

		<para>There is a special stub that is required for testing the JHttp transports so that actual web requests can be simulated
		and assertions can be made about the results. To set these up, copy the file jhttp_stub.php to a web server and add the address
		to your config file with the config variable <code>$jhttp_stub</code>.</para>
	</section>

    <section>
      <title>Running the Tests</title>

      <para>You can run the tests by going to the platform root directory and executing <command>phpunit</command></para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Coding Standards Analysis</title>

    <para>In order to improve the consistency and readability of the source code, we run a coding style analysis tool everytime
    changes are pushed in the repo. For new contributions we are going to be encorcing coding standards to ensure that the coding
    style in the source code is consistent. Ensuring that your code meets these standards will make the process of code
    contribution smoother.</para>

    <para>The Joomla Platform sniffer rules are written to be used with a tool called PHP_CodeSniffer. Please see the <ulink
    url="http://pear.php.net/package/PHP_CodeSniffer">PHP_CodeSniffer Pear Page</ulink> for information on installing
    PHP_CodeSniffer on your system.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Running CodeSniffer</title>

      <para>You can run CodeSniffer by going to the platform root directory and executing <command>phpcs --report=checkstyle
      --report-file=build/logs/checkstyle.xml --standard=/path/to/platform/build/phpcs/Joomla /path/to/platform</command></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Known Issues</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>There is currently an issue with running the Code Sniffer on the Simplepie library. Pointing the sniffs at the
          libraries/joomla directory or below will avoid the issue.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
</appendix>
