<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE preface PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "../Developer_Manual.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<appendix id="appe-Joomla_Platform_Manual-Analysis">
  <title>Configuring Code Analysis Tools</title>

  <section>
    <title>Running Unit Tests</title>

    <para>Before code gets pulled into the master repository, the unit testing suite is run to ensure that the change candidates
    do not leave trunk in an unstable state (i.e. all tests should pass at all times). In order to make the process of getting
    your code accepted it is helpful to run these tests locally to prevent any unexpected surprises.</para>

    <para>The Joomla Platform unit tests are developed for use with PHPUnit 3.6, which is the latest stable version as of August
    2011. Please see the <ulink url="http://www.phpunit.de/manual/3.6/en/installation.html">PHPUnit Manual</ulink> for information
    on installing PHPUnit on your system.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Configuring Your Environment: The Database</title>

      <para>Standard unit tests run against a <ulink url="http://www.sqlite.org/quickstart.html">Sqlite</ulink> in memory
      database for ease of setup and performance. Other than <ulink url="http://www.sqlite.org/quickstart.html">installing Sqlite</ulink>
      no manual intervention or set up is required. The database is built at runtime and deleted when finished.
      </para>

      <para>To run the specific database tests:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Create your database and use the appropriate database-specific DDL located in
          tests/suites/database/stubs to create the database tables required.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>In the root directory, copy the file named phpunit.xml.dist, leaving it in the same
          folder and naming it phpunit.xml.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Uncomment the php block and include the const line(s) related to the database(s) you will be testing.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Set up the database configuration values for your specific environment.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>

	<section>
	  <title>Configuring Your Environment: The JHttpTransport Test Stubs</title>

	  <para>There is a special stub that is required for testing the JHttp transports so that actual web requests can be simulated
	  and assertions can be made about the results. To set these up, you'll need to do the following:</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>In the root directory, copy the file named phpunit.xml.dist, leaving it in the same
            folder and naming it phpunit.xml.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Uncomment the php block and include the "JTEST_HTTP_STUB" const.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The default file path for the const assumes that you have checked out the Joomla Platform to the web root
            of your test environment inside a folder named "joomla-platform".  If this is not the case, you can change
            the path to suit your environment and, if need be, copy the file from its default location to be available within
            your web environment.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Running the Tests</title>

      <para>You can run the tests by going to the platform root directory and executing <command>phpunit</command></para>

      <para>Alternatively, if you have Ant installed on your system, you may run the unit tests by going to the platform root
      directory and executing <command>ant phpunit</command> to execute the tests on classes located under the libraries/joomla
      directory or executing <command>ant phpunit-legacy</command> to execute the tests on classes located under the
      libraries/legacy directory.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Coding Standards Analysis</title>

    <para>In order to improve the consistency and readability of the source code, we run a coding style analysis tool everytime
    changes are pushed in the repo. For new contributions we are going to be enforcing coding standards to ensure that the coding
    style in the source code is consistent. Ensuring that your code meets these standards will make the process of code
    contribution smoother.</para>

    <para>The Joomla Platform sniffer rules are written to be used with a tool called PHP_CodeSniffer. Please see the <ulink
    url="http://pear.php.net/package/PHP_CodeSniffer">PHP_CodeSniffer Pear Page</ulink> for information on installing
    PHP_CodeSniffer on your system.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Running CodeSniffer</title>

      <para>You can run the CodeSniffer by going to the platform root directory and executing <command>phpcs --report=checkstyle
      --report-file=build/logs/checkstyle.xml --standard=/path/to/platform/build/phpcs/Joomla /path/to/platform</command></para>

      <para>Alternatively, if you have Ant installed on your system, you may run the CodeSniffer by going to the platform root
      directory and executing <command>ant phpcs</command></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Known Issues</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>There is currently an issue with running the Code Sniffer on the Simplepie library. Pointing the sniffs at the
          libraries/joomla directory or below will avoid the issue.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
</appendix>
