<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "../../Developer_Manual.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<section>
  <title>JControllerBase</title>

  <section>
    <title>Construction</title>

    <para>The constructor for <classname>JControllerBase</classname> takes an optional <classname>JInput</classname> object and an
    optional <classname>JApplciationBase</classname> object. If either is omitted, the constructor defers to the protected
    loadInput and loadApplication methods respectively. These methods can be overriden in derived classes if the default
    application and request input is not appropriate.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Usage</title>

    <para>The <classname>JControllerBase</classname> class is abstract so cannot be used directly. The derived class must
    implement the execute method to satisfy the interface requirements. Note that the execute method no longer takes a "task"
    argument as each controller class. Multi-task controllers are still possible by overriding the
    <methodname>execute</methodname> method in derived classes. Each controller class should do just one sort of 'thing', such as
    saving, deleting, checking in, checking out and so on. However, controllers, or even models and views, have the liberty of
    invoking other controllers to allow for HMVC architectures.</para>

    <example>
      <title>Example controller</title>

      <programlisting>/**
 * My custom controller.
 *
 * @package  Examples
 *
 * @since   12.1
 */
class MyController extends JControllerBase
{
	/**
	 * Method to execute the controller.
	 *
	 * @return  void
	 *
	 * @since   12.1
	 * @throws  RuntimeException
	 */
	public function execute()
	{
		echo time();
	}
}

// Instantiate the controller.
$controller = new MyController;

// Print the time.
$controller-&gt;execute();</programlisting>
    </example>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Serialization</title>

    <para>The <classname>JControllerBase</classname> class implements <interfacename>Serializable</interfacename>. When
    serializing, only the input property is serialized. When unserializing, the input variable is unserialized and the internal
    application property is loaded at runtime.</para>
  </section>
</section>
