<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xml:id="ch1">
  <title>Source Code Management</title>

  <section>
    <title></title>

    <para>Before we start talking about what code should look like, it is
    appropriate to look at how and where the source code is stored. All
    serious software projects, whether driven by an Open Source community or
    developed within a company for proprietary purposes will manage the source
    code is some sort of source or version management system. Joomla currently
    employs two different systems. One system is for the files that form the
    product distributed as the Joomla CMS, and the other is for the files that
    are distributed as the Joomla Platform. Each system is described
    below.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>The Joomla Platform</title>

    <para>In April 2011 the Joomla project decided to formally split off the
    core engine that drives the Joomla CMS into a separate project with a
    separate development path called the Joomla Platform. The Joomla Platform
    is a PHP framework that is designed to serve as a foundation for not only
    web applications (like a CMS) but other types of software such as command
    line applications. The files that form the Joomla Platform are stored in a
    Distributed Version Control System (DVCS) called Git hosted at
    github.org</para>

    <para>You can learn about how to get the Joomla Platform source code from
    the Git repository from the following page: &lt;permalink to
    developer.joomla.org staging page&gt;</para>

    <para>Because Git treats the concepts of file revision numbers
    differently than Subversion, the repository revision number is not
    required in files (that is, the @version tag is not necessary).</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Compliance Tool</title>

    <para>TODO Mention something about CodeSniffer and the custom Joomla sniff
    standard for PHP files. The Sniff is based on the standard outlined in
    this document. For more information about how code standards are enforced 
    see the analysis appendix of the manual.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
