<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<appendix xml:id="app1">
	<title>Configuring Code Analysis Tools</title>

	<sect1>
		<title>Running Unit Tests</title>

		<para>Before code gets pulled into the master repository, the unit testing suite is run to
		ensure that the change candidates to not leave trunk in an unstable state (i.e. all tests
		should pass at all times). In order to make the process of getting your code accepted it
		is helpful to run these tests locally to prevent any unexpected surprises.</para>
		
		<para>The Joomla Platform unit tests are developed for use with PHPUnit 3.5, which is the
		latest stable version as of August 2011. Please see the
		<link href="http://www.phpunit.de/manual/3.5/en/installation.html">PHPUnit Manual</link> for
		information on installing PHPUnit on your system.</para>
		
		<sect2>
			<title>Configuring Your Environment</title>
			
			<para>At this point in time you will get a bunch of failed unit tests if you attempt to execute
			them without first creating a database, populating it, and configuring the unit tests to be able
			to locate the correct database using the correct user.</para>
			
			<para>To do this, perform the following steps:</para>
			
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>Create a database and a database user with full access to the database.</para>
				</listitem>
				
				<listitem>
					<para>Populate the database by executing the ddl.sql file found in the tests directory.</para>
				</listitem>
				
				<listitem>
					<para>Copy the config.php-dist file to config.php (in the tests directory) and edit the host, user,
					password and db values as appropriate (this step can be skipped if your database is on localhost,
					is named joomla_ut, your user is named utuser and the password is ut1234.</para>
				</listitem>
				
			</itemizedlist>

		</sect2>

		<sect2>
			<title>Running the Tests</title>
			
			<para>You can run the tests by going to the platform root directory and executing <command>phpunit</command></para>
			
		</sect2>
		
		<sect2>
			<title>Known Issues</title>
			
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>There is currently a cache test that will fail the first time you run the tests. If you run the tests a
					second time it should pass.</para>
				</listitem>
				
			</itemizedlist>
			
		</sect2>
		
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1>
		<title>Coding Standards Analysis</title>
		
		<para>In order to improve the consistency and readability of the source code, we run a coding style analysis tool everytime
		changes are pushed in the repo. For new contributions we are going to be encorcing coding standards to ensure that the coding
		style in the source code is consistent. Ensuring that your code meets these standards will make the process of code contribution
		smoother.</para>

		<para>The Joomla Platform sniffer rules are written to be used with a tool called PHP_CodeSniffer. Please see the
		<link href="http://pear.php.net/package/PHP_CodeSniffer">PHP_CodeSniffer Pear Page</link> for
		information on installing PHP_CodeSniffer on your system.</para>

		<sect2>
			<title>Configuring Your Environment</title>
			
			<para>The Joomla project has written custom code sniffer rules for use with PHP_CodeSniffer. Unfortunately, these is a
			limitation in PHP_CodeSniffer which means that in order to use the custom rules they either have to be symlinked or copied into
			the PEAR directory.</para>
			
			<para>The build/phpcs/Joomla directory must be copied into CodeSniffer standards directory. On Ubuntu 11.04 this directory is
			<filename>/usr/share/php/PHP/CodeSniffer/Standards</filename>. On Macports this directory is
			<filename>/opt/local/lib/php/PHP/CodeSniffer/Standards</filename>. Other systems and configurations will vary.</para>

		</sect2>

		<sect2>
			<title>Running CodeSniffer</title>
			
			<para>You can run CodeSniffer by going to the platform root directory and executing
			<command>phpcs --report=checkstyle --report-file=build/logs/checkstyle.xml --standard=Joomla /path/to/platform</command></para>

		</sect2>

		<sect2>
			<title>Known Issues</title>
			
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>There is currently an issue with running the Code Sniffer on the Simplepie library.
					Running from inside the Joomla folder will avoid this issue.</para>
				</listitem>
				
			</itemizedlist>
			
		</sect2>

	</sect1>
</appendix>
