<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE preface PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "../Developer_Manual.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<chapter id="chap-Joomla_Platform_Manual-Introduction">
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <para>This is the introduction to the Joomla Platform.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Folder Structure</title>

    <para>The following outlines the purpose of the top-level folder structure of the Joomla Platform as found in the Github
    repository.</para>

    <para>/build contains information relevant for building code style reports about the platform. Output from various automated
    processes may also end up in this folder.</para>

    <para>/docs contain developer manuals in DocBook format.</para>

    <para>/libraries contains all the server-side PHP code used in the Joomla Platform API.</para>

    <para>/media contains any client-side resources used by the platform.</para>

    <para>/tests contains all of the unit tests used for quality control.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Bootstrapping</title>

    <para>Bootstrapping the Joomla Platform is done by including <filename>/libraries/import.php</filename> in your application.
    This file will initiliase a number of constants if they are not already defined by the developer prior to including the
    import.php file:</para>

    <simplelist>
      <member><constant>JPATH_PLATFORM</constant> - The path to the Joomla Platform (where <filename>loader.php</filename> or
      <filename>platform.php</filename> is located, usually in the same folder as <filename>import.php</filename>).</member>

      <member><constant>IS_WIN</constant> - A boolean value, true if the platform is Microsoft Windows based.</member>

      <member><constant>IS_MAC</constant> - A boolean value, true if the platform is Apple OSX based.</member>

      <member><constant>IS_UNIX</constant> - A bollean value, true is the platform is some flavor or Unix, Linux or similar (but
      not Mac).</member>
    </simplelist>

    <para>The bootstrap file will loader the <classname>JPlatform</classname> and <classname>JLoader</classname> classes and also
    <classname>JFactory</classname>, <classname>JException</classname> (legacy), <classname>JObject</classname>,
    <classname>JRequest</classname> (legacy), <classname>JText</classname> and <classname>JRoute</classname>. Depending on the
    version, it may also register classes in a transitional state that do not conform to the auto-loader standards.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Minimalistic Approach</title>

      <para>If required, the bootstrap file (import.php) can be ignored and a custom solution can be implemented (such as if the
      core JFactory class is to be overriden).</para>

      <example>
        <title>A custom, minimalist bootstrap example</title>

        <programlisting>// Define the base path.
define('JPATH_PLATFORM', '/path/to/platform/');

// Load the platform version and loader classes.
require_once JPATH_PLATFORM . '/platform.php';
require_once JPATH_PLATFORM . '/loader.php';

// Setup the autoloaders.
JLoader::setup();

// Do custom registration if required.</programlisting>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Legacy Platform</title>

      <para>The Joomla Platform also supports a legacy tree for API. It includes many classes that are only used by the Joomla
      CMS, or classes and packages that have been upgraded and introduced backward compatibility issues. Bootstrapping the legacy
      Joomla Platform is done by including <filename>/libraries/import.legacy.php</filename>. This instructs the auto-loader to
      look for classes in the legacy tree first, and then in the core tree.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Platform Version</title>

    <para>Platform version information can be found by accessing the JPlatform class.</para>

    <xi:include href="classes/jplatform.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Class Auto-loading</title>

    <para>The Joomla Platform implements a class auto-loader removing the need for the developer to include files by hand, or by
    using a fall to the <function>jimport</function> function (this is now discourage in favor of using
    <methodname>JLoader::register</methodname>). Only class names that begin with upper case "J" will be considered for
    auto-loading. Following the "J" prefix, the class name must be in camel case and each segment of the name will represent a
    folder path below <filename>JPLATFORM_PATH/joomla</filename> where the last segment of the name is the name of the class file.
    If there is only one part to the class name, the auto-loader will look for the file in a folder of the same name. Folder names
    must be in lower case.</para>

    <example>
      <title>Valid auto-loading cases</title>

      <para><classname>JDatabase</classname> should be located in
      <filename>JPATH_PLATFORM/joomla/database/database.php</filename></para>

      <para><classname>JDatabaseQuery</classname> should be located in
      <filename>JPATH_PLATFORM/joomla/database/query.php</filename></para>

      <para><classname>JDatabaseQueryMysql</classname> should be located in
      <filename>JPATH_PLATFORM/joomla/database/query/mysql.php</filename></para>
    </example>

    <para>There is no limit to the depth to which the auto-loader will search, providing it forms a valid path based on the camel
    case natural of the class name. Note that while acronyms and names such as HTML, XML and MySQL have a standard presention in
    text, such terms must observe camel case rules programmatically ("HTML" becomes "Html", "XML" becomes "Xml" and so on).</para>

    <para>The JLoader class allows additional customisation including, but not limited to, providing the ability to override core
    classes and cater for classes that do not conform with the auto-loader naming and path convention.</para>

    <xi:include href="classes/jloader.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
  </section>
</chapter>
