<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "../Developer_Manual.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<chapter id="chap-Joomla_Platform_Manual-jauthorisation">
  <title>The Authorisation Package</title>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>The authorisation package is awesome.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Interfaces</title>

    <para>Three interfaces are provided to support the authorisation package.</para>

    <section>
      <title>JAuthorisationAuthorisable</title>

      <para>The <interfacename>JAuthorisationAuthorisable</interfacename> interface requires a class implement an
      <methodname>authorise</methodname> method.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>JAuthorisationAuthoriser</title>

      <para>The <interfacename>JAuthorisationAuthoriser</interfacename> interface requires a class implement an isAllowed method
      and a setRules method. The authorisation package provide two concrete classes implementing this interface (see
      <classname>JAuthorisationAuthoriserDefault</classname> and <classname>JAuthorisationAuthoriserRoot</classname>). These align
      with the strategies required for the Joomla CMS.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>JAuthorisationRequestor</title>

      <para>The <interfacename>JAuthorisationRequestor</interfacename> interface requires a class implement a getIdentities
      method. The method must return an array of identities but there are no rules for how that array is constructed other
      than it must be consistent with the rules by which the identities will be authorised.</para>

      <para>A common strategy is to employ this interface in "user" objects and return an array of integers. Positive integers
      would represent the groups the user belongs to and a single negative integer would represent the id of the user.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Classes</title>

    <para>The classes in the Authorisation package.</para>

    <section>
      <title>JAuthorisationFactory</title>

      <para>The JAuthorisationFactory class provides a method to retrieve a type of authoriser.</para>

      <example>
        <title>Using the JAuthorisationFactory class</title>

        <programlisting>try
{
	$authoriser = JAuthorisationFactory::getInstace()
		-&gt;getAuthoriser('default');
}
catch (Exception $e)
{
	// Handle exception.
}</programlisting>
      </example>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>JAuthorisationRule</title>

      <para>The <classname>JAuthorisationRule</classname> class helps the developer to build a ruleset either programmatically,
      using the <methodname>set</methodname> method, or by merging from multiple sources, using the <methodname>merge</methodname>
      method.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>JAuthorisationAuthoriserDefault</title>

      <para>This is the default authoriser that emulates the rule strategy that is employed by the Joomla CMS. Authorisation of
      actions are treated as denied unless otherwise specified (implicit deny). Authorisation will be denied if any identity for
      an action is explicitly denied even if other identities explicitly allow the action.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>JAuthorisationAuthoriserRoot</title>

      <para>The root authoriser emulates a strategy whereby the requestor is always authorised to perform any action regardless of
      any set rules.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
